Guide to the Jim Fouratt Papers
Fouratt (Jim) Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Series yo
Jim Fouratt papers
1965 2016
GEN MSS 1453
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
241.83 Linear Feet
(209 boxes)
Fouratt, Jim
Scope and Contents
The collection spans the years 1965 to 2016 and consists of correspondence, writings, printed material, financial papers, photographs, audiocassettes, videocassettes, buttons, t-shirts, and other papers and realia relating to Jim Fouratt's life and involvement with political and counterculture activities, gay rights and AIDS activism, and nightclubs and the music industry. Papers relating to political and counterculture activism document Fouratt's involvement with movements and events of the late 1960s and early 1970s, including the Youth International Party (Yippies) and the 1967 Central Park Be In. Papers relating to gay rights and AIDS document Fouratt's activism and work with organizations including the Gay Liberation Front and ACT UP. Papers relating to nightclub management document his work at Hurrah!, Danceteria, and other clubs, and papers relating to band management document Fouratt's work with a wide range of musical acts. Band demos and video recordings document new wave, rock, and punk acts that performed or sought to perform at clubs managed by Fouratt during the early to mid-1980s. Buttons collected by Jim Fouratt span a variety of political causes and many musical acts active during the 1980s. T-shirts collected by Fouratt represent a range of musical acts, clubs, and political causes.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Glenn Horowitz Bookseller, Inc. on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2015.
Jim Fouratt
Jim Fouratt (born June 23, 1941, in New Brunswick, New Jersey) is an American gay rights activist, writer, nightclub promoter, and music industry manager. In the late 1960s and early 1970s Fouratt was a member of the Yippies and helped organize the Central Park Be In. He was present at the Stonewall Rebellion, co-founded the Gay Liberation Front, and has been an active contributor to many groups focused on gay rights and AIDS-related activism. Fouratt has worked in the music industry in several capacities, ranging from managing nightclubs such as Hurrah! and Danceteria in the late 1970s and early 1980s to working as vice president of A&R at Mercury Records in the late 1990s. He has also worked as an actor and journalist.
Arrangement
Organized into eight series: I. Papers relating to political and counterculture activism, 1965-1974. II. Papers relating to gay rights and AIDS activism, 1968-2016. III. Papers relating to nightclub and band management, circa 1978-2000s. IV. Band demos and recordings, circa 1980s. V. Video recordings of band performances, 1979-1987. VI. Buttons, 1965-1980s. VII. T-shirts, 1977-1990. VIII. Realia, circa 1980s-2000s.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Boxes 55-142, 208 (audiovisual material): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 209 (born digital): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
AIDS activists United States; AIDS (Disease) Social aspects United States; Counterculture United States History 20th Century; Discotheques New York (State) New York; Gay activists; Gay liberation movement United States; Gay rights United States; Music trade United States; New wave music; Nightclubs New York (State) New York; Political activists; Popular culture United States; Punk rock music United States; Rock music 1971-1980; Rock music 1981-1990; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Buttons (information artifacts); Photographs; T-shirts; LGBTQ resource; Fouratt, Jim; ACT UP (Organization); Danceteria (Nightclub); Gay Liberation Front (New York, N.Y.); Hurrah (Nightclub); Youth International Party
- Papers relating to political and counterculture activism, 1965 1974; Series I; 4.67 Linear Feet; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains papers documenting Jim Fouratt's involvement with political and counterculture movements and events of the late 1960s and early 1970s, including the Youth International Party (Yippies), the Purple Star Tribe, the 1967 Central Park Be In, and the 1969 Woodstock Music and Art Fair. Papers include correspondence, photographs, artwork, printed material, ephemera, notebooks, and other papers. Also includes scripts and photographs documenting Fouratt's work as an actor.
  - Freedom of Information file, 1981 (Box 1)
    Consists of the results of Jim Fouratt's multiple requests to varying United States governement agencies for information about files kept about him under his legal name and his aliases.
  - Notebook, photograph, and ephemera, 1970 1971 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, flyers, and ephemera, 1969 1972 (Box 1)
  - Printed materials, flyers, and ephemera, circa 1971 (Box 1)
  - Purple Star Tribe papers, 1971 June (Box 1)
    Includes photographs, calendar page, flyer, notes, and a poem from Fouratt's trip to Gay Pride Week in Austin Texas with the Purple Star Tribe and the Stompin' Lilac Society. Some of the photographs were used for the groups' work on Iconoclast Comes Out Volume 1, number 31.
  - Correspondence, 1965 1969 (Box 1)
  - Photographs and artwork, circa 1969 (Box 1)
  - Notes and ephemera, 1965 1969 (Box 1)
  - Business files and notes, 1965 1969 (Box 1)
  - Press releases, flyers, and political tracts, 1965 1969; 4 folders (Box 1)
    Includes papers from the Communications Company, White Panther Party, Yippie!, and other groups. Also includes drawings, correspondence, and other related papers.
  - Correspondence, receipts, and other materials, 1965 1970 (Box 1)
  - Flyers, newspaper clipping, and correspondence, 1967 1971 (Box 1)
    Includes Digger flyers from 1967 for a "Free Store," the "Be In" at Central Park and others from the "Communication Company/NY."
  - Freelandia airline membership card and informational materials, 1973 1974 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, notes, and writings, 1970 1974 (Box 1)
    Much of the the correspondence is addressed to "Digger" Jim.
  - Ephemera, flyers, and other materials, 1966 1974 (Box 1)
  - Revolutionary materials, 1968 1970 (Box 1)
  - Be In handbills, 1967 March 26 (Box 2)
    114 handbills created by Peter Max for the Easter Central Park Be In on March 26th, 1967. Also includes the original mechanical.
  - Be In flyers, notes and newspaper clippings, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1960 1979 (Box 2)
    Includes photographs of protests, actors, musicians, activists, and Fouratt as an actor in a play.
  - Photographs of protests, actors, musicians, and activists, 1960 1979 (Box 2)
  - Woodstock Music and Art Fair passes, 1969 (Box 2)
    Includes a press parking pass, a performer pass for Chip Monck from Woodstock Ventures, and a courtesy pass for photographer Peter Hujar.
  - Notes and notebooks, circa 1969 (Box 2)
    Includes notes about Richard Neville with a photograph of Fouratt at a protest, poetry and other materials.
  - Financial and employment documents, 1964 1969; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Volkswagen and insurance documents, 1970 1979 (Box 2)
  - Notes and ephemera, circa 1967 (Box 2)
    Includes a note and magazine clipping from Clive Davis.
  - Eye magazine letterhead and clippings, 1968 1969 (Box 2)
    - 3 reel to reel tapes by Al Cooper, It's a Beautiful Day, and one titled "Rocks Greatest Hits", circa 1969; 3 Audiotape Reels (Box 208)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - New Times, 1972 1979 (Box 2)
  - Advertising materials, including photographs and clippings, for the band It's a Beautiful Day, circa 1969 (Box 2)
  - Script for Bent by Martin Sherman, newspaper clipping, and ephemera, 1967 1979 (Box 3)
  - Scripts, 1960 1979; 3 folders (Box 3)
    Includes the following titles: The Motion of History by Amiri Baraka, The Freaking Out of Stephanie Blake by Richard Chandler, Isolation by Lee Kissman, and others.
  - Photographs, 1960 1979; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Printed materials, circa 1971 (Box 4)
    Includes a "Purple Star Tribe house copy" of Quicksilver Times, July 1971, and an annotated copy of Iconoclast Comes Out volume 1 number 3, from Dallas News. Also includes a Weather Underground poster inscribed "To Digger - with love Camo, Lorenzo, Possom."
  - Partial copies of Liberation News, 1972 (Box 4)
- Papers relating to gay rights and AIDS activism, 1968 2016; Series II; 6.42 Linear Feet; (12 boxes)
  This series contains papers documenting Jim Fouratt's activism in support of gay rights and in reaction to the AIDS epidemic. Documentation includes correspondence, writings, printed materials, notebooks, posters, flyers, and other papers. A significant portionof the papers relate to Fouratt's involvement with groups including the Gay Liberation Front, Wipe Out AIDS, the Federation of AIDS Related Organizations, and ACT UP.
  - New York AIDS Network, The Center Proposal, 1983 (Box 5)
    Consists of materials relating to planning a center for the gay and lesbian community.
  - Notebook, circa 1984 (Box 5)
    Notebook contains Jim Fouratt's notes on AIDS and substance abuse, gay and lesbian parenting, and Europe's responce to the AIDS crisis.
  - AIDS related materials, 1980 1989 (Box 5)
  - AIDS Network materials, 1983 1990; (5 folders) (Box 5)
    Includes materials documenting Jim Fouratt's involvment with ACT UP, Gay Activist Alliance of New York, and the 1988 NY War Conference. Also includes correspondence, anti-AMA propaganda, and the Last Will and Testament of Max Navarre (aka Michael Hurlebaus).
  - Literature on nitrite inhalants, undated (Box 5)
  - Printed and photocopied materials relating to mental health from the AIDS Institute of New York and other organizations, circa 1984 (Box 6)
  - Pre-ACT UP! AIDS awareness materials, 1982 1992; (6 folders) (Box 6)
    Includes notes, flyers, publications, and correspondence from Wipe Out AIDS (WOA) and the Federation of AIDS Related Organizations (FARO). Publications include How to Have Sex In An Epidemic, The Case for the Temporary Closure of Commercial Sex Establishments During the AIDS crisis: Throwing Out the Baths with the Bath Water, and others.
  - How to Have Sex In An Epidemic and related materials, 1980 1989 (Box 6)
    Includes the original pamphlet How to Have Sex In An Epidemic, related materials, and other printed materials.
  - Wipe Out AIDS materials, 1980 1989; (6 folders) (Box 7)
    Includes correspondence, printed materials, a ledger, and a funding proposal to New York State AIDS institute. Also includes publications about diet and nutritional supplements.
  - Gay Liberation Front and radical feminist materials, 1969 1973; (6 folders) (Box 8)
    Includes documents, flyers, and printed material relating to the Gay Liberation front and radical feminism. Publications include A Gay Manifesto by Carle Wittman, The GLF calendar, pamphlets from The Feminists, Gay Flames pamphlets, Echo of Sappho, early writings by T. Grace Atkinson, Diana di Prima's Revolutionary Letters published by The Communication Company/NY, and others.
  - Gay rights and AIDS health information, 1980 1999; 5 folders (Box 9)
    Includes correspondence, photocopies, and newspaper clippings about AIDS public health issues. Also includes materials relating to the advocacy group ACT UP.
  - Wipe Out AIDS and AIDS health information, 1980 1989; (4 folders) (Box 10)
    Flyers, correspondence, and related materials for Wipe Out AIDS. Also includes information on AIDS health and diet, notes, and printed materials.
  - Political tracts and other materials, 1965 1989; (5 folders) (Box 11)
    Political tracts include "Lesbians and the Health Care System," "20 Questions about Homosexuality," "Notes Toward a Gay Consiousness," and others. Also includes related correspondence and ephemera.
    - Talks about AIDS, 1980 1999; 7 Audiocassettes (Box 208)
  - Political tracts, correspondence, and other materials, 1965 1976; (3 folders) (Box 11)
    Includes correspondence largely pertaining Fouratt's arrest in 1971. Other materials include a Gay Liberation Front political tract, typescripts, flyers, and ephemera. Also includes a copy of Jean Genet's "The Man Condemned to Death" translated by Dinana di Prima and a lightly annotated carbon typscript of John Giorno's "Cum."
  - Political posters and printed materials, 1965 1976; (3 folders) (Box 12)
    Includes Symbionese Liberation Army poster, printed guide to May Day in Washington D.C., and a Purple Star Tribe house copy of "Iconoclast Comes Out".
  - Weather Underground rainbow painting and photographs, 1971 (Box 12)
    Includes photographs of Jim Fouratt, Michael Bumblbee, and Gay Liberation Front protests.
  - Notes, faxes, correspondence, and publications relating to ACT UP, 1990 1992 (Box 13)
  - Gay and lesbian community reference materials, 1992 1994 (Box 13)
    Includes Lesbian and Gay Directory of Services and Resources, National Gay and Lesbian Task Force press materials, and Twelve Steps and Twelve Traditions of Recovery for Gay Men's Incest and Sexual Abuse Survivors Anonymous.
  - Faxes, correspondence, flyers, notes, and ephemera concerning sexual politics and AIDS health, 1985 1995; (2 folders) (Box 13)
  - Federation of AIDS-Related Organizations (FARO), 1983 August 1983 October (Box 14)
    Consists of meeting minutes, including a proposal for a documentary film about FARO.
  - Safe sex for bath houses, 1983 1985 (Box 14)
    Includes writings by Jim Fouratt and Michael Callen on how bath club owners could raise conciousness of AIDS with their patrons.
  - "Bits and pieces J.F.", 1990 1999 (Box 14)
    Includes writings by others, clippings, cartoons, and other papers.
  - Faerie Dish Rag, 1991 1992 (Box 14)
    Includes copies of the gay community publication and related materials.
  - Writings of others, 1984 1994 (Box 14)
    Includes papers titled "The Norlin paper" and "Letter from Michio to Wipe Out AIDS Friends" and others.
  - Artists and AIDS activists, circa 1989 (Box 14)
  - International AIDS Network materials, 1990 1999 (Box 14)
    Includes materials relating to gay rights and AIDS in Hait and Japan.
  - ACT UP materials and gay rights ephemera, 1980 1999 (Box 14)
  - News clippings and ephemera related to safe sex and gay rights, 1994 1995 (Box 14)
  - Gay rights and AIDS awareness art projects, 1980 1999 (Box 14)
  - Pamphlets, flyers, and other ephemera, 1980 1999 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence, promotional materials, and ephemera, 1970 1999 (Box 14)
  - Gay rights political strategy materials, circa 1978 (Box 14)
  - Miscellaneous gay rights and AIDS activism materials, 1970 1989 (Box 14)
  - Research files, 1970 1999 (Box 15)
  - AIDS activism materials, 1980 1989 (Box 15)
    Includes materials from various regional organiziations in the northeast United States.
  - Lesbian and Gay Service Center founding documents, circa 1983 (Box 15)
  - Transcript of an interview covering Fouratt's life from birth through the early 1970s, circa 1991 (Box 15)
  - Writings, undated (Box 15)
    Includes one partial, untitled typescript and one manuscript titled "Comming Out Of The WPP."
  - Newspaper and magazine clippings and ephemera, 1970 1999 (Box 15)
  - Organizational records, 1980 1999 (Box 15)
    Includes records relating to Baltimore H.E.R.O., New York AIDS Network, National Gay Health Education Foundation, and other groups. Also includes conference papers and reports.
  - Healthy eating and wok cooking cartoon, undated (Box 15)
  - Photograph negatives, 1980 1999 (Box 15)
- Papers relating to nightclub and band management, 1978 2009; Series III; 39.25 Linear Feet; (41 boxes)
  This series consists of papers related to Jim Fouratt's work as a manager of nightclubs and musical acts. Papers include correspondence, writings, legal documents, photographs, press releases, mailing lists, address books, business records, promotional ephemera, clippings, and other materials. Nightclub management materials document Fouratt's work with Average Normal, Inc., Dare Entertainment, Inc., Danceteria, Hurrah!, Studio 54, CBGB's, Limelight, and others. Documentation of musical acts includes papers relating to Richard Lloyd, Swans, Two Nice Girls, Pylon, Ornette Coleman, Hot Lunch, and others.
  - Rolodex, 1970 1989; (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Rolodex, 1970 1989 (Box 17)
  - Message notebooks and day planner, 1978 1979; (3 folders) (Box 18)
  - Notebooks, 1980 1989; (2 folders) (Box 19)
    Managment notes and film criticism.
  - CBGB's, Danceteria, and Hurrah! letterhead, 1970 1989 (Box 19)
  - Legal and incorporation files for Dare Entertainment Inc., 1982 1983 (Box 19)
  - Dare Entertainment Inc. promotion related correspondence, 1990 1999 (Box 19)
  - Hot Lunch, Max's flyers, 1978 (Box 19)
  - Legal contracts with The Radio Band of America and related correspondence, 1986 (Box 19)
  - Promotional materials for bands and clubs, 1980 1989 (Box 19)
    Inlcudes flyers, cards, notepads, and other ephemera.
    - Floppy disks, 1990
      Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
      - SEE NO EVIL, 2016-genm-0050-0001; 1 5.25_floppy_disk (Box 209)
      - SEE NO EVIL, 2016-genm-0050-0002; 1 3.5_floppy_disk (Box 209)
  - Mailing lists and lables, 1980 1999; (3 folders) (Box 19)
  - DARE management, artist files, 1980 1999; (4 folders) (Box 19)
    Includes music-related ephemera and correspondence, invoices and other materials pertaining to Richard Lloyd, Tim Miller, Animal Slaves, and others.
  - Danceteria advertising maquettes, 1980 1989 (Box 20)
  - Danceteria flyers, promotional materials, and newspaper clippings, 1980 1989; (3 folders) (Box 21)
    Includes materials from Blitz, On The Waterfront, and Modern Classix.
  - Danceteria business files, 1979 1986; (5 folders) (Box 21)
    Includes opperational memos, correspondence, artist contracts, legal papers, and other business papers.
  - Ephemera and related materials, 1980 1989 (Box 21)
  - Ideas and clippings for promotional materials, 1950 1989 (Box 21)
    Includes magazine and newspaper clippings, photographs, and other materials used to create advertising and flyers.
  - Jim Fouratt headshots and resume, 1980 1989 (Box 21)
  - Photographs, 1980 1989 (Box 21)
    Includes photographs of locations around Danceteria and other clubs, autographs, and pictures of Jim Fouratt with various bands.
  - Personal materials, 1940 1989 (Box 21)
    Consists of photographs and other materials including the following:
    Cooper, Dennis. "XMAS 1982" Folio w/ photographs inscribed by Cooper to Fouratt and Miller.
    Tim and Dona McAdams. "Democracy in America" inscribed by Miller to Fouratt. Signed by Miller and McAdams. #31 in an edition of 50. 1984.
  - Post-Punk and New Wave band files, 1981 1984; 3 folders (Box 22)
    Consists of correspondence, promotional materials, show flyers, and photographs relating to Fad Gadget [Frank Tovey], Young Marble Giants, R.E.M., Jayne County, Human Sexual Response, The Grown Ups, and others.
  - Correspondence and other business papers related to Rhino Records, 1985 1991 (Box 22)
  - Average Normal, Inc. materials, circa 1982 (Box 22)
    Includes IOU documentation from Keith Lavine of Public Image Ltd. for money borrowed from Jim Fouratt.
  - Post-Punk and New Wave files, 1981 1984; 2 folders (Box 23)
    Promotional materials, band flyers and photographs.
  - Post-Punk and New Wave files, 1981 1984; 3 folders (Box 24)
    Promotional materials, band flyers, photographs, related reciepts and correspondence.
  - Business records, 1980 1999 (Box 25)
    Accounting, consulting, publicity, and talent booking records for Studio 54. Also includes VIP mailing lists, letters of support from Fouratt's tenure at Danceteria.
  - Mailing list, 1980 1999; 3 folders (Box 25)
  - Promotional materials, 1980 1989 (Box 25)
    Postcards, stickers, and other materials.
  - Operational and business records, 1980 1989; 13 folders (Box 26)
    Materials from Hurrah!, Danceteria, and Average Normal, Inc.
  - Operational and business records, 1980 1989; 10 folders (Box 27)
    Includes guest lists.
  - Band and promotional materials, 1980 1989 (Box 27)
  - Average Normal mailing lists, 1980 1989; 5 folders (Box 28)
  - Average Normal Inc. letter head, 1980 1989 (Box 28)
  - Ephemera, 1980 1999; 2 folders (Box 28)
    Includes posters, stickers and postcards.
  - Operational and business papers relating to club and talent management, 1980 1989 (Box 29)
  - Notebooks, 1980 1989 (Box 29)
  - Limelight, Danceteria, and Hurrah!, 1980 1999; 3 folders (Box 29)
    Postcards, flyers, finacial records, and statements. Also includes concert ephemera, photographs, and Danceteria pinback buttons.
  - Promotional materials and business papers, 1980 1999; 8 folders (Box 30)
    Promotional materials relate to Limelight, Max's Kansas City, and Danceteria, as well as musical acts that Fouratt managed. Business papers include correspondence, reciepts, insurance, taxes, and contracts.
  - Promo pack for Swans, circa 1984 (Box 30)
    Contains lyrics, photographs, and artwork.
  - Personal papers and materials, 1980 1989 (Box 30)
    Includes acting resume, therapy notebook, and a pocket edition Mao Tse-Tung.
  - Musical act management, Two Nice Girls, 1980 1999; 8 folders (Box 31)
    Consists of materials documenting Fouratt's management of the band Two Nice Girls, including promotional materials, maquettes for album artwork, contracts, press clippings, reciepts, and other related materials.
  - Musical act management, Richard Lloyd, 1980 1999; 2 folders (Box 31)
    Consists of papers documenting Fouratt's management of former Television guitarist Richard Lloyd, includes promotional materials, contracts, press clippings, reciepts, and other related materials.
  - Business files relating to Pylon, 1989 1991; 3 folders (Box 31)
    Materials include, correspondence, receipts, legal papers, ephemera, and newspaper clippings.
  - Receipts, travel documentation, and other business related documents, 1980 1999; (4 folders) (Box 32)
  - Research, 1988 1991 (Box 32)
    Includes correspondence and photocopies.
  - Hot Lunch artwork and maquettes, 1970 1989; 3 folders (Box 33)
    Includes artwork by Michael Shore, photographs, flyers, and other materials for the band Hot Lunch.
  - Band flyers and other ephemera, 1970 1989 (Box 33)
    Includes a Throbbing Gristle press release,and a "Trials of Sylvia Likens" poster signed by Kate Millett, 1978, and others papers.
  - Legal documents and contracts, 1970 1979; 2 folders (Box 33)
    The bulk of these materials relate to the legalities of rent, and eviction.
  - Resumes with photographs, 1970 1989; 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Actors Equity Association, 1977 1979 (Box 33)
    Includes minutes, notes, lists, reports, and other related materials.
  - New York calling list, undated (Box 33)
  - Business file, 1974 1977; 2 folders (Box 33)
    Includes statements, canceled checks, reciepts, and other related materials.
  - Resumes with photographs, 1960 1989; 2 folders (Box 34)
  - Correspondence and photographs, 1979 1998; 2 folders (Box 34)
    Correspondence from friends, artists, and musicians related to Fouratt's club and band mamangment.
  - Business papers, notes, and correspondence, 1980 1999 (Box 34)
  - Flyers and promotional materials, 1975 1999 (Box 34)
    - Mona Lisa Overdrive, 1993
      - Mona Lisa Overdrive, 2016-genm-0050-0003; 1 CD-R (Box 209)
      - Mona Lisa Overdrive, 2016-genm-0050-0004; 1 CD-R (Box 209)
    - 33 rpm record by The Scientific Americans, 1980; 1 Phonograph Record (Box 208)
  - Writings by others, 1980 1989 (Box 34)